<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Immutability on JDORO.println</title><link>https://jdoro.github.io/jdoro-blog/tags/immutability/</link><description>Recent content in Immutability on JDORO.println</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jdoro.github.io/jdoro-blog/tags/immutability/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>React Best Practices: Immutability</title><link>https://jdoro.github.io/jdoro-blog/posts/2024-06-11-react-immutability/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jdoro.github.io/jdoro-blog/posts/2024-06-11-react-immutability/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Immutability is an important concept in React development. Without a solid
understanding of it, you would certainly struggle with state management in your
React applications. In this blog post, we will explore the concept of
immutability, its importance in React, and how to apply it effectively in your
projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-is-immutability"&gt;What is Immutability?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Immutability is the ability of an objects value to be changed after it;s&lt;br&gt;
been created. In simpler terms, once an object is created, its value cannot be
changed. If you want to &amp;ldquo;change&amp;rdquo; the object you need to create a new object with
the desired changes. Employing immutability in your application helps you
ensure that the data inside an object remain consistent and predictable. If
an object is passed into a function and you mutate it within that function, the
caller of the function can no longer be certain that the object will remain
unchanged. This can lead to bugs that are difficult to track down.
Immutability also allows for comparison optimizations by only checking if the
reference to the object has changed, rather than comparing all the values in the
entire object.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>